<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.6">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-15T17:29:12+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Mantra Medical Ltd</title><entry><title type="html">Workflow Integration</title><link href="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/workflow-integration" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Workflow Integration" /><published>2020-04-16T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T16:56:04+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/workflow-integration</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/workflow-integration">&lt;p&gt;Effective healthcare requires robust systems and processes that work to ensure efficiency even under stress conditions. Once established, healthcare processes produce entrenched workflow pathways that staff become familiar and comfortable with. Effective processes go some way to ensuring that key tasks are completed regardless of workload and help staff to know what to do and when to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Any new innovation that disrupts entrenched workflow is neither desirable nor likely to be adopted. Failure to consider existing workflow while designing products has been stated as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statnews.com/2020/02/10/10-reasons-why-health-care-startups-fail/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;one of the top-ten reasons for medical device startups failing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Despite this, many medical devices fail to engineer deep workflow integration into their design. Too many new products focus on the perceived features and benefits rather than the ability of staff to use the device in practice. If a device requires a change in staff behaviour in order to gain any benefits available, it will not see widespread adoption and will fail to meet its objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It is important for all medical device manufacturers to remember that while &lt;b&gt;problems need disrupting, people do not&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Focusing on features and benefits while paying insufficient attention to workflow integration is a serious mistake. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK2638/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;As this paper by Carol Cain and Saira Haque suggests&lt;/a&gt;, if insufficient attention is given to existing staff workflow while designing medical devices, staff are forced into a decision &amp;mdash; either use the device at the expense of another task, or neglect the device and fail to take advantage of any benefits it could otherwise offer.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Cain and Haque argue that a deep understanding of healthcare workflow processes is necessary to ensure that any additions to those processes are acceptable. Their first premise is that any failure of healthcare staff to complete a task is not necessarily down to the complexity of that individual process. Rather, in many cases it is the interaction of multiple processes that causes disruption. In the event of multiple processes interacting, even the simplest tasks can become impossible to complete:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;when workflow processes are looked at in isolation, the processes appear quite logical (and even efficient) in acting to accomplish the end goal. It is in the interaction among the processes that complexities arise. Some of these interactions hide conflicts in the priorities&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;cite&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK2638/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cain C, Haque S. Chapter 31: Organizational Workflow and Its Impact on Work Quality&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span&gt;Patient Safety and Quality: An Evidence-Based Handbook for Nurses&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;/cite&gt;
        &lt;/blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Many medical device manufacturers fall into the trap of analysing the complexity of using their devices in isolation. This is a mistake. To ensure seamless adoption of new devices, they must be simple to use even when multiple processes are interacting and should keep any disruption to the conduct of process workflow to an absolute minimum. Even simple tasks are neglected when workflow is disrupted and priorities conflict.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Infection control is a great example of an important healthcare activity that can suffer from this effect. Basic clinical hygiene is performed readily during quiet times but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25278571&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;becomes increasingly difficult to undertake as workload increases.&lt;/a&gt; If hygiene activities are considered only in isolation it is difficult to comprehend why routine cleaning of commonly-used clinical tools is ever neglected. For example, wiping down a pulse oximeter or blood pressure cuff after use with an antiseptic wipe takes only a few seconds and is known to be effective if performed. However, this viewpoint is far too simplistic and misses the effect of multiple interacting processes on staff capacity. Existing infection prevention methods do not adequately address this.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Routine cleaning is highly susceptible to the phenomenon documented by Cain and Haque &amp;mdash; despite apparent simplicity, it is difficult to accommodate into clinical care and exceptionally challenging to deliver during time-pressured acute situations (when, many would argue, it is needed most).&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The failure of existing infection prevention methods to integrate seamlessly into existing staff workflow underpins their failure to eradicate healthcare associated infections, and goes some way to explaining why HCAIs continue to cost the UK economy £1bn per year.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A new approach is required that puts workflow integration at the forefront of product design, disrupting the problem without disrupting the people that work within it. At Mantra Medical, our infection control concepts are designed entirely around complete workflow integration. We believe that workflow integration combined with product automation will ensure universal compliance with infection control practice, leading to a safer and cleaner healthcare environment. &lt;a href=&quot;/innovations/&quot;&gt;Learn more about our infection control innovations&lt;/a&gt; and how we will deliver safer healthcare.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this article, please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; and we will be happy to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Effective healthcare requires robust systems and processes that work to ensure efficiency even under stress conditions. Once established, healthcare processes produce entrenched workflow pathways that staff become familiar and comfortable with. Effective processes go some way to ensuring that key tasks are completed regardless of workload and help staff to know what to do and when to do it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Emergency Measures Critical Times</title><link href="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/emergency-measures-critical-times" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Emergency Measures Critical Times" /><published>2020-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T16:58:07+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/emergency-measures-critical-times</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/emergency-measures-critical-times">&lt;p&gt;As the coronavirus pandemic begins to reveal itself as a global disaster, attention turns to what else we can do to slow the spread of the contagion.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Much of mainland Europe is currently in a state of enforced lockdown and social distancing measures are underway across much of the world. At the same time, however, hospitals are filling up and the risk of infection spread amongst the vulnerable becomes higher with every passing day.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We have previously written about the dangers of overlooking the needs of non-coronavirus patients caught up incidentally in the crisis. With the level of media interest focused on the outbreak, it is easy to forget that patients suffering with all other healthcare problems continue to arrive in hospital, day after day. It has always been imperative that we prevent the spread of healthcare associated infection to and between these patients; this is now more important than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;At Mantra Medical, we face a dilemma. We are a small, pre-market company that is developing devices to reduce the risk of infection transmission caused by routine patient interactions. Pulse oximeters and blood pressure cuffs are used on every hospital patient in the world. Existing systems and methods for infection prevention make it extremely difficult to deliver consistent and effective cleaning of these devices, meaning they act as a source of infection spread as they move from patient to patient. It is our belief that the unique, automated products we have developed can provide consistent cleaning in a system already under massive pressure. All hospital patients could benefit from these products, and others like them, that are being made ready for use in the real world. We want to help make a difference. However, although our products are designed and almost ready to go, we do not yet have regulatory approval for our devices.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Under normal circumstances it would take us a year to gain the required approvals. This will be far too late to help in the fight against coronavirus. We feel that our devices are needed immediately. Therefore, after much reflection, we have taken the exceptional step of writing to the governing body in the UK &amp;mdash; the MHRA &amp;mdash; to request that a special measure be brought into play to allow our devices to be made available to patients without waiting a year for normal regulatory procedures. Called Article 59 MDR, this provision allows for derogation (a bypassing) from normal conformity assessment procedures in times of a public health emergency. Sensibly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hilldickinson.com/insights/articles/covid-19-new-mhra-guidance-and-processes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the MHRA has indicated&lt;/a&gt; that they recognise the need for derogation in the present circumstances and are open to approving the limited use of some non-CE marked devices. We await their decision on our devices.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We remain absolutely committed to the safety and performance of our medical devices. We do not seek Article 59 approval in order to derogate from our safety obligations in any way. Rather, we seek approval to derogate from a bureaucratic process that is designed to keep patients safe, but that has the potential in the current circumstances to cause delays that patients can ill-afford.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/innovations/&quot;&gt;More information about our devices&lt;/a&gt; can be found on our website. If you believe that these devices should be available to patients now, please write to your MP, the Secretary of State for Health and Social Care, and to the MHRA to express your support.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/downloads/article_59_derogation-mantra_medical_ltd.pdf&quot;&gt;I enclose a copy of the letter (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; we have sent to the Secretary of State for Health and Social Care.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;A sincere thank you for your support.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;
        Dr Paul Hercock&lt;br /&gt;
        CEO &amp;amp; Founder, Mantra Medical Ltd
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this article, please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; and we will be happy to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As the coronavirus pandemic begins to reveal itself as a global disaster, attention turns to what else we can do to slow the spread of the contagion.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Medical Device Regulation Covid 19</title><link href="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/medical-device-regulation-covid-19" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Medical Device Regulation Covid 19" /><published>2020-03-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T16:56:08+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/medical-device-regulation-covid-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/medical-device-regulation-covid-19">&lt;p&gt;The Covid-19 pandemic means challenging times for everyone in healthcare. Exceptional measures are being taken to manage the intense challenges posed by the coronavirus outbreak. Whether you are on the medical frontline, supplying goods or manufacturing products, the way we all work is changing and we must all stand ready to make adaptations.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The UK government has already taken the exceptional step of asking large manufacturers such as JCB and Unipart to switch manufacturing from car and vehicle parts to production of ventilators. The general public is being asked to reduce social contact to a minimum and the most susceptible in society are soon to be asked to protect themselves by self-isolating for as long as 12 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In the midst of the chaos it is easy to overlook the basics. While it is a priority to ensure that life saving products are made available to staff and patients as quickly as possible, it is also vital that the safety and performance of these products is subject to the appropriate level of scrutiny. The medical device market is one of the most tightly regulated sectors in the world for good reason &amp;mdash; unsafe or ineffective medical devices could cause far more problems than they solve. In May 2020, the new Medical Device Regulations (MDR) formally replace the MDD and bring forth a more stringent regulatory framework for all aspects of medical device development, production and surveillance.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;As with everything though, a balance is needed. Analogies to a war-time footing are being readily made and there is a growing acceptance that a sensible flexing of usual rules is required to meet the highly unusual demands of the present time. Bringing a new medical device to market normally requires that manufacturers navigate complex conformity assessment procedures that, with a current shortage of notified body capacity, can take over a year to work through. This is not only commercially problematic for the companies involved; if the devices in question stand to benefit patients in the light of the current public health emergency, it could be strongly argued that the regulatory processes, if too stringent, could have a net negative impact.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The Medical Device Regulations (MDR) themselves acknowledge this. Article 59 MDR allows for emergency derogation from standard conformity assessment procedures in the event of a public health emergency. In other words, if the government (via their competent authority, the MHRA) feels that a device not yet in possession of a CE mark is crucial in addressing a public health emergency, they can allow normal procedures to be bypassed and make the device available to patients while they urgently need it.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Medical device regulatory processes remain vital. As a pre-market company with developmental medical devices that have not yet passed through the conformity assessment process, Mantra Medical is absolutely committed to the requirements for medical device safety and performance mandated by the Medical Device Regulations. In our opinion, however, it is crucial that a sensible balance is reached. Appropriate compromises must be made to allow highly-relevant devices to avoid regulatory backlogs, ensuring that they reach staff and patients who need them urgently.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;We urge the government to consider applying Article 59 MDR where appropriate to meet the demands of the current crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this article, please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; and we will be happy to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">The Covid-19 pandemic means challenging times for everyone in healthcare. Exceptional measures are being taken to manage the intense challenges posed by the coronavirus outbreak. Whether you are on the medical frontline, supplying goods or manufacturing products, the way we all work is changing and we must all stand ready to make adaptations.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Coronavirus Outbreak Challenges Hospital Infection Control</title><link href="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/coronavirus-outbreak-challenges-hospital-infection-control" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Coronavirus Outbreak Challenges Hospital Infection Control" /><published>2020-03-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T16:56:12+01:00</updated><id>https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/coronavirus-outbreak-challenges-hospital-infection-control</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.mantramedical.co.uk/articles/coronavirus-outbreak-challenges-hospital-infection-control">&lt;p&gt;Since news emerged in December 2019 of an outbreak of a novel coronavirus infection in Wuhan, China, concern amongst the international healthcare community has understandably been rising.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;It is a novel coronavirus that causes the condition Covid-19, characterised by a dry cough, high fever and difficulty breathing. Concerns stem not only from its ability to cause severe respiratory distress, but also the absence of a direct treatment, lack of a vaccine, and an apparent R0 of between 2 and 3 (in other words, on average, each infected person will infect 2-3 others). This outbreak has the ingredients of a major global pandemic and attention must turn to prevention wherever possible.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Because the virus is novel and coronavirus infections in humans are comparatively rare, the underlying immunity in the population is virtually non-existent. For this reason and many others, this is much more than &quot;just the flu&quot;. Evidence emerging from China, Italy and Iran &amp;mdash; the countries worst affected so far &amp;mdash; shows that the condition can produce very serious respiratory distress, especially in those with underlying health conditions. The disease threatens to overwhelm healthcare systems as caseload grows and our very way of life is under threat.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;The novel coronavirus spreads predominantly in two ways:&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;ol&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Through air&lt;/b&gt; - mostly inhalation of viral particles expelled from an individual who is shedding the virus&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Through contaminated surfaces&lt;/b&gt; &amp;mdash; viral particles stick to hands following contact with a virus-hosting surface, and hands are then brought into contact with the nose, mouth or eyes.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ol&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Social distancing measures are part of the strategy to limit spread through airborne transmission and handwashing advice seeks to address other routes, but in the context of hospital care we believe that additional measures will be necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Perhaps one of the most important challenges that hospitals will face is also one of the most forgotten about. No matter how many coronavirus patients need hospital care, there will be no let up in the rate of other serious health conditions unrelated to the virus. Although elective surgery is sure to be cancelled as more and more facilities are needed to care for Covid-19 patients, there will still be patients with myocardial infarction, oncological disorders, renal problems, gastrointestinal disorders, and so on. Not only will this further strain the system, but hospitals must also consider how to avoid spreading the virus to patients attending for other reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;One obvious strategy is segregation, ensuring that 'red zones' dedicated to management of Covid-19 are separated from other clinical areas. But the circulation of staff, visitors and supplies means that, almost inevitably, there is a risk of viral infections spreading to other areas.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;In our view, a major focus must be on ensuring good basic clinical hygiene. Every surface that contacts any patient for any reason must be scrupulously clean. Basic clinical tools such as pulse oximeters and blood pressure cuffs must be decontaminated between every patient to prevent them from acting as a vector of infection spread. A global pandemic produces a perfect storm for infection transmission: as the workload burden on healthcare staff increases to unsustainable levels, the opportunities to perform routine cleaning diminish. And yet, infection control activities are more critical than ever.&lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Innovation is the key weapon. New ideas are required that can deliver consistent cleaning with no extra burden on staff. In the meantime we urge healthcare providers to focus on basic clinical hygiene and to not underestimate the possibility of incidental spread of coronavirus via contaminated hospital surfaces.
        &lt;/p&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;If you have any questions about this article, please &lt;a href=&quot;/contact&quot;&gt;contact us&lt;/a&gt; and we will be happy to answer them.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Since news emerged in December 2019 of an outbreak of a novel coronavirus infection in Wuhan, China, concern amongst the international healthcare community has understandably been rising.</summary></entry></feed>